so what is
death and what is
parinibana
there's a difference it's a big
difference
because of some people you it sounds
like um
is it like the it's the real well you
cannot have
an objective perspective on both at the
same time
because obviously pertains to existence
so
you're either within death
from which you can't see paranibana or
if you transcend death as an arahant
then you can see where paranibana is so
to speak
so it's not you can't just examine them
as these two separate phenomena because
you are either one or the other
either one pertains to you or the other
so as the buddha described death is when
when the mind is not free from greater
version delusion
and the point of view pretty much
continues wandering on and
pre-manifesting some song samsara yeah
so death as as
commonly thought of death
is simply a wandering on
a change a change yeah a major change a
major change
but not a complete difference
well yeah yeah but the thing is like
again a person who is not free from death
a person who is not free from death
person who is not free from great
division delusion
is not free of those things because of
the wrong views
about the nature of themself about the
nature of their experience as a whole
about the nature of the world
so from their point of view even the
view of death
will be skewed and based upon
misconceptions so that's why like you can say i can say
so that's why like you can say i can say
oh yes death is not the end
most people with the wrong view when
they hear that it would sound as if
ah so it's not the end but you can't
even fathom what not
end of death is unless you're already
starting to be free from death
free from greed aversion delusion free
from lack of perspective
so it's wandering on it's death if you
want to find out
where death is for you personally in
your experience
you have to look where the things you're
scared of most
that's what death is not where your idea
of death is
because that's where people would often
conflate you know you have this
external notion of death based on what
you see in here
and that's kind of not personal like you
need to
or it's it's easier to not make it
personal so then people develop notions
that yeah i'm not fear i'm not afraid of
yeah i'm not fear i'm not afraid of
death everybody dies
they're not afraid of their idea of
death if you're truly not afraid of
death which is the mother of all fears then
which is the mother of all fears then
you wouldn't have
any fear towards anything in the world
so is that the case
are you fear free in regard to
everything and anything
if so then you can say i'm not afraid of
death but if oh i'm still scared of this i'm
but if oh i'm still scared of this i'm
still worried about that
oh you and i have nowhere near being
free from fear of death
there was that example that i remember i
had a number of times
i think they did that in the
concentration camps
on jews they were asking well they were
examining like psychological effects of
the ones they were about to be killed
um and they were wanted to see and they
kind of came to a conclusion if i
remember collected that
they were more afraid people in the
concentration camps
were more afraid of being
shunned and abandoned by their group
there by their peers by their community
because basically you know that was
their identity
in these extreme circumstances of a
concentration camp so they were more
afraid of that
then of a gas chamber
so it's like oh see people are more
afraid to be
not accepted by the peers then they're
afraid of death
no they're more afraid to not be
accepted by their peers
then they're afraid of their idea of
death but the actual death existentially
but the actual death existentially
speaking is where their death of their
personality was
which was oh my community this group
that i depend on
they basically they dismiss me they
don't like that i don't exist for them
anymore that was more frightening
ah so that's where the death is
practically speaking
so that's what i mean you find where
you're afraid
if you follow that thread that's where
death is
that's what death is death of my
reputation whatever for somebody's reputation for
whatever for somebody's reputation for
somebody's health
for somebody's status for somebody's
wealth doesn't matter
change of an unpleasant kind it affects
existentially again partakes in the nature of death
again partakes in the nature of death
correctly
that's what death is whatever threatens
my identity
yeah so again if you if somebody is
reflecting and they can't
seem to be afraid of death because
they're reflecting on the level of their
idea of death not on the level of what actual
of death not on the level of what actual
death is
which you would discover through first
finding fear
that represents it
so being shunned from my community or
friends or whatever i mean that's that
is like from
for many like you know these were this
kind of
experiment was done in these extreme
circumstances but it's not too different
out in the world people are
fundamentally want to be accepted
don't want to be rejected they they they
want to be approved of
by the ones that they value by the ones
that they regard dear
to them family whatever friends
and you know how much people are afraid
of what people say about me
they might kind of pretend they don't
care but deep down you always feel it
when somebody criticizes you or somebody
speaks badly of you you're always
touched by that and you cannot stop that
because you don't know how
so that's already something ah so you
are afraid
of the worldly winds as the weather
would say fame disrupted
lost gain what what are these things
what all these things have in common
it's change we discussed that before so
you are afraid
of the change that affects you adversely
that it's unpleasant so you are you're
afraid of suffering
you still fear suffering and
death is the ultimate change the
ultimate suffering
which means if you think you can still
have sufferings that you're afraid of
sufferings that you're afraid of
unpleasantness that you don't like that
you want to avoid that you fear
experiencing and at the same time think but you're
and at the same time think but you're
not afraid of death
that's not death that's great that's
contradiction yeah exactly i'm not
afraid of
experiencing things i don't want yeah so
it's that's i mean the reason why death is
that's i mean the reason why death is
such a proliferated idea
out there for people is because it's the
most frightening thing so
cover-up systems are pretty much
deployed right away as soon as you start
experiencing things not going your way
you start creating a buffer zone between
you and the circumstances and the world
and then like sometimes you know people
get shocked by witnessing death but if
you subject them to repetition of that they
subject them to repetition of that they
will go numb
they will manage to rebuild that idea so
they don't feel
that that applies to them existentially
and that's the the you know
the common statement now everybody will
die i fully understand that
thus i accept my death now you accept
the theoretical aspect that you
proliferated off death
because if you were to die next second
will you not be afraid or you would
but that idea the acceptance of the idea
on that abstract level
allows you to feel safe while actually
you're not
that's why you need you actually need to
make effort to uncover
all the things that you use to clutter
the unpleasant truths
internally in order to be able to start
practicing mindfulness of death
correctly for example
because the whole life revolves around
avoiding it covering it up
cultivating only the change you want not
the change you don't want
and then pretending that the change that
you don't want yet you're not in control
of
well ignoring it that's the best you can
do ignore the fact that you are liable
to death
this very moment not tomorrow not in two
days
and that's all that's already like an
abstract thought for an undeveloped mind
so that's when you need to make this
effort and go through this like mental
drilling to keep reminding yourself
until it takes place and then you'll
feel it
then you feel it very much i'm subject
to change
being affected by it yeah change yeah
and and again
that's why the the sense restraint needs
to be developed beforehand
because sense restraint is just the
pursuit of change
to its pleasure or pleasant change so
you intentionally are accepting change
you want change just you won't change in
one direction but you don't want to
change things change in another direction but
things change in another direction but
for as long as you're cultivating
acceptance of change
means when things change in the
direction you don't want it to change
you will suffer
you are seeking change through seeking
centrality you want to change the state
of affairs
and because of that when things change
against your wishes
you will also be affected because you
are not actually
mentally understanding that
liability to experiencing change as a
problem you don't see change is a
problem you only see certain type of change in
you only see certain type of change in
the problem the one that you don't like
but changing itself you very much
welcome you you very much want
and because of that
it will have to happen the times will
have to occur where you will experience
change that you don't want
because change is fundamentally not in
your control and you know that
so if your sense if you practice sense
restraint just to see that the nature of change is
just to see that the nature of change is
a problem
not necessarily things change for good
things change for bad
doesn't matter what matters is that
things change
what matters is the change means things
are not in your control that's already
the problem
so you don't need to wait for the
unfortunate change for things to change to worse in
change for things to change to worse in
order to see that nature
on the contrary usually if you wait for
that it might be too late
so death is the ultimate change
change to what you don't you you cannot
know that but you know
this will change the distance
disintegration of
senses it's a change change of the
domain of sight sound smell taste touch
but it's a it's a core change in the
core yet here you are
spend your whole life before that final
change of death by by cultivating by
relishing by delighting in change
towards pleasure in change away from
pain so you keep yourself bound to that which
so you keep yourself bound to that which
is subject to change
thus when you change the way you don't
want it to you will suffer
and that's the buddha said like in brief
what is suffering
being united with what you don't want
and being separated from what you want
that's it that's the rule that's the in
the core that's
one way or the other being uh
well attached or connected to change
well no what's in common
you want to see what's in common to be
united with what you don't want
and being separated from what you want
change is in common
things have changed so you realize okay
so can you stop the change
can you prevent things from changing
inconceivable so what can you do then oh i can stop
so what can you do then oh i can stop
delighting
in pleasant change and stop trying to
outrun the unpleasant change so the problem is
the unpleasant change so the problem is
not in things changing
the problem is in you craving for a
particular type of change
and craving against another particular
type of change
either way you're bound by change you're
under the thumb of change
so when it changes one way or the other
you will be affected by it
but it's just that you ignore that
because sometimes you're affected by
pleasure but then equally you're bound to be
but then equally you're bound to be
affected by pain by lack of pleasure
which would be painful so being affected
by change is the problem
not the pleasure that comes out of it or
pain that comes out of it
but as long as you only see pleasure get
pleasure avoid pain
you're not seeing the nature of i'm
subject to change
and the the problem with that and the
problem with that exactly exactly
you don't see the problem and and that's
again that's what these wrong views as i
said come into play
well everybody will die but if you're
honest and if you don't actually if you think
and if you don't actually if you think
about it rationally you realize well
everybody will die cannot apply to me
dying because i can only witness others people
because i can only witness others people
other people's death
externally which will never be how i can
experience my own death
so your own death experience of it is
always internal
yet here the notion you're trying to
apply to it everybody will die thus
are not worried is only based on the
external perception which is completely
secondary to that which will be affected by death
to that which will be affected by death
when it comes to you
your sense organs so if you really want
to see
how it would be if you were to die
imagine yourself going blind going deaf
becoming an invalid losing a sense of
smell touch ah that's closer now to what death
touch ah that's closer now to what death
is why
because now you're contemplating about
the loss of sense organs
not just particular sense objects have
changed which kind of remained
keeps your assumption of sensory organs
remaining intact
well keeps that assumption alive oh
everybody will die that's
i'm not worried okay would i be worried
if i go blind
if i cannot see things anymore would i
be worried if i cannot hear things
anymore oh that would be extremely unpleasant
oh that would be extremely unpleasant
why is that because you're so dependent
on sense objects that's what death is
or rather death is much closer to that
than what you think death is
the fundamental change they will uproot
your sense organs not
just sense objects that come and go so
to speak
yet the idea that you the people keep
trying to apply to it
is the idea based on just sense organ
observation object observation
yeah he dies that dies everything
changes i'll change
okay you want to contemplate change
contemplate cessation of your sense
organs while you're still alive
and see how uncomfortable that will be
yeah will that affect you yeah of course
yeah but if you're truly not affected even if
but if you're truly not affected even if
like a
clear comprehending the possibility of
going blind
deaf invalid crippled
losing your limbs if your mind remains
equanimous in face of it okay then you
know you're practicing rightly
so to contemplate death then
find that which scares you that which
you don't want to accept
and that's the direction that will come
from
that change in the most fundamental
sense they will uproot you not come for you to
they will uproot you not come for you to
witness it
which is change of sense objects not the
sense organs
and that's the big difference whether
you're an observer of it
or that which has been swept by it
and if you're an observer of it that's
not the death because you can't observe
death because it sweeps
your powers of observation comes from
behind him so to speak
so being subject to death means
being subject to death even correctly
what means being subject to change it's
not in your control yeah maybe you're
subject to that so when you're not subject to
to that so when you're not subject to
death anymore
when you're not subject to death anymore
yeah like the arrowhead is not subject
to death
means the change well means things that
are subject to change the body the sense
organs he has relinquished he has no emotional
he has relinquished he has no emotional
bond with
no wrong views misconceiving them no
ownership all these these different aspects of uh
all these these different aspects of uh
of wrong views he has uprooted so when
those things change he will remain
unaffected because he's not bound by those things
he has abandoned them
so yeah he cannot die
yeah exactly so in from that point of
view party nibana is even more than
death we spoke about that before so death
we spoke about that before so death
means basically you're still take you
you will still be taking up things
one way or the other because you haven't
uprooted that
wrong view in regard to the nature of
change in regard to the nature of
ownership
but another hand has approved all of
that so when his sense organs
disintegrate there is truly the inconceivable end
there is truly the inconceivable end
so to speak so the buddha would only
when he would speak about the other he
would say his aggregates break apart
for somebody who is not an arahant
aggregates don't break apart
that's what samsara is bound by
aggregates that you are misunderstanding
that you're misconceiving that you're
owning
that's what was said whether you
remember the previous life 500 previous
lives all you remember is these five upgrades
all you remember is these five upgrades
that you have right now so that's your
framework for an arahant that framework
for an arahant that framework
disintegrates because he's not picking
it up because he has a proof to the
ownership of it
so in that sense that's what i mean
ibana is then truly the the
disintegration the death of
no more change after that so to speak
but again saying no more change
kind of implies designation what
parinibana is and
that's meanwhile that can only be true
theoretically practically speaking
as i said you either partake in death or
deathless paranoid so don't have a notion that you
paranoid so don't have a notion that you
you think you can think about in ibana
unless in these colloquial terms while
you're not free from death
and even if you're free from death then
you wouldn't be thinking paranibana
your experience is that experience
that's going to end in paranabana when
aggregates break apart
so that's why i kind of tried to avoid
talking about this because for most
people who become speculative
they think they can start thinking about
part in ibana and death and how it
relates to it as if somehow practically
relevant for them but it's not
the only practical relevance there is
find that which scares you find that
which upsets you
find that which emotionally disturbs you
well and then imagine death being at the
other end of that
not at the other end of whatever you
observed and assume death to be
being shunned by the community oh i
cannot live by i cannot sleep at night
people thinking badly of me people not
accepting me people think i'm an idiot
people think i'm a fool
oh there you go that's what scares you
that's where your death is
so what then what do you do then
contemplate it develop strength in
regard to it don't try to outrun it and
certainly don't try to cover it up
you want to what's the nature of it you
want to and again the only way you can
see the nature of that which scares you
is to stop running away from it or
pretending it's not there
so you're scared of being shunned by
your community why is that
oh because it's on the gratuitous
pleasure of safety that i was deriving
on a kind of being part of a bigger
thing than i am
but were you really a part of a bigger
thing or were you just assuming yourself
your individual point of view as
belonging to something great in other
words can the community make you step outside
can the community make you step outside
of yourself and your own responsibility
and your own point of view inconceivable
so you were literally distorting things
for your own emotional gain
of safety and now that became apparent
when you looked at that which scared you
and you're already stepped closer to to
being affected by that fear now you can
endure it
that's what i said like a wise monk who
is practicing would be enduring the
unpleasant words of others
in the same sense you endure the
elements so you can't stop that
and you can't stop the discomfort of
people criticizing you
because it feels like an attack on your
existence but you can stop being
affected by it
and then yeah you have no problem oh
it's a bit cold today
oh yeah today i have people criticizing
me
but you see their criticisms clearly
well you you won't lose perspective
because you're not trying to emotionally
cover it up
so you will even you will be able to see
if it's a just criticism or injustice
criticism and either way you wouldn't feel
and either way you wouldn't feel
affected by it just criticism okay
like when the buddha made those rules
people criticized like yeah they have a
point like he wasn't upset about it he said
like he wasn't upset about it he said
okay stop doing that
so he would just make a rule for
something
but when people don't have their
perspective even when they
are criticized irrationally people have
no just basis for criticizing them but
they criticize them out of ill will or
whatever foolishness they have people will be
foolishness they have people will be
affected and they will try to
cater and appease to the people that
criticize them even if they know
oh this is nonsense this is simply not
true because again they're not acting from
because again they're not acting from
that rational recognition or
more importantly from that ability to
endure the discomfort from which you
will get perspective upon it they're
acting from that emotional need to
remove the pain
and have pleasure even if it's
completely rational
injust and baseless criticism that's
when people fear blame
for stop not fear righteous just blame
and don't fear him just no just fear
being blamed well i better not do it for
somebody in my mind but
what am i about to do is that
unwholesome is that harmful no no no
so what am i feeling i'm feeding my
rational projected idea of blame
affecting me
and that's weakness which means now
you're just cultivating your own
weakness
but seeing that you start to uncover
that exactly
you start seeing it by being able to
endure it well
but basically starting to endure it but
say no i will not outrun it i will not
justify myself
i will endure it you might even review
your actions and you get filled with
doubt what if what if you and your dad
as well
and then that pressure you get used to
it so it's pressuring you less and then
you get to see more
but the problem is pressure means look
away you look away you can't get
to see it so in order to see through
that pressure you have to endure it
and that's exactly what contemplation of
that is the
fundamental pressure
of this in its core my existence
will change will sweep me will take me
away like a flood
is the mother of all fears
i am subject to change and it can come
in any direction
yeah at any point so you'll find things
that you find little changes that scare you
you find little changes that scare you
that bother you
what if people say this why do people
again change of the environment you want
i want people to approve of me look now
you're experiencing change
towards the people disapproving of you
and that's bothering you a lot
i want these kind of pleasures
fundamentally exactly
all you want is to avoid pain and
experience pleasure
but you will recognize if you stop
blindly trying to outrun it
that this discomfort of that fundamental
change of death is
unavoidable not nothing you do
in this life on account of sense sense
objects can upload that because everything is a
can upload that because everything is a
result of it
so that's what the buddha realized when
oh i'm subject to death means
yeah i can live in a palace protected
for that's all i have family children
gratitude all of it all
yet relationship between me and my own
death that fundamental change
is just fully remains unchanged as in
i'm still
equally liable to it and nothing i do in
the world can come in between and
protect me from it
so then he realized that the only way to
protect yourself from that fundamental
change is to abandon the world
the ownership of it the ownership of the
sense organs
the lighting in the world which yeah is
assumed the ownership of the sense
organs is assumed through the lighting
and sense objects
you imply ownership of organs so we're
talking about in each of those yeah
well that's what changes yeah change
means a nature death
complaint contemplation of death
connotation in nature
doesn't mean end it means change
if it were to mean end all you have to
do is die and become another and
pardon ibana and sure enough there were
wrong views like that back in india when
the buddha was describing them in the
suttas but no anichia means subject to change
but no anichia means subject to change
perpetual
change in this life next life when it's
lifetime subject means you have within
basically the framework within the
container of things that change
against you sometimes that against you
is felt pleasantly sometimes that
against you is felt unpleasantly either
way you are subjected to it like being like
you are subjected to it like being like
being swept
in a in a in a flood
sometimes you bump into things it hurts
sometimes you enjoy the ride on the wave
but either way you are swept you have no
stable ground and that's the problem not
that oh i avoid these rocks and i go on these
oh i avoid these rocks and i go on these
pleasant waves no the problem is that
you have you cannot stop it
but yeah that's that's what change is
the fundamental
uh non-control that that affects you you